阿尔法小分队荣誉译制
翻：@ErrorEnvyEnchant 校：@Auriance 压制：@Mihael_Ho
长期招募 详情见微博置顶@阿尔法小分队科教组
大家好 我是凯莉·安 欢迎来到计算机科学速成课
Hi, I'm Carrie Anne, and welcome to Crash Course Computer Science!
上一集 我们讨论了几个经典算法
Last episode, we discussed a few example classic algorithms,
比如数字排序和图的最短路径
like sorting a list of numbers and finding the shortest path in a graph.
我们没有说算法所需的数据
What we didn't talk much about, is how the data the algorithms ran on
是如何储存在计算机内存里的
was stored in computer memory.
【约翰·格林，美国作家，大学时双修了英语和宗教学】
你不希望你的数据像约翰·格林的大学寝室一样乱
You don't want your data to be like John Green's college dorm room,
【声明：图中不是约翰·格林】
食物 衣服 纸张扔的到处都是
with food, clothing and papers strewn everywhere.
相反我们希望结构化数据 以便于组织
Instead, we want our data to be structured, so that it's organized,
【图中也不是约翰·格林】
使数据读取更容易
allowing things to be easily retrieved and read.
所以计算机学家使用了数据结构
For this, computer scientists use Data Structures!
我们上集已经介绍了一个基本数据结构 数组
We already introduced one basic data structure last episode, Arrays,
某些语言中也叫列表或向量
also called lists or Vectors in some languages.
它是在内存中储存的一系列数值
These are a series of values stored in memory.
(有了它) 变量每次就不限于保存单个数字 像j=5这种
So instead of just a single value being saved into a variable, like 'j equals 5',
而使我们能定义一整列数字
we can define a whole series of numbers,
并保存到数组变量中
and save that into an array variable.
为了找到数组里的某个数 需要指定索引
To be able to find a particular value in this array, we have to specify an index.
几乎所有编程语言的数组索引都从0开始
Almost all programming languages start arrays at index 0,
【索引从1开始的语言，如COBOL, Fortran, Lua, Mathmatica, MATLAB, Smalltalk等】
用方括号语法[ ] 访问数组元素
and use a square bracket syntax to denote array access.
例如 我们相加数组j中第一个和第三个元素
So, for example, if we want to add the values in the first and third spots of our array
并保存到a中 就可以写一行这样的代码
'j', and save that into a variable 'a', we would write a line of code like this.
数组在内存中的储存方式很直观
How an array is stored in memory is pretty straightforward.
为了简便 假设编译器选择内存地址1000储存我们的数组
For simplicity, let's say that the compiler chose to store ours at memory location 1,000.
这个数组有7个数字 它们先后存储在内存里
The array contains 7 numbers, and these are stored one after another in memory,
如图所示
as seen here.
这样当我们写 j[0] 时  计算机访问内存地址1,000
So when we write "j index of 0", the computer goes to memory location 1,000,
内存偏移地址是0 取值5
with an offset of 0, and we get the value 5.
如果想取 j[5]  程序到内存地址1,000
If we wanted to retrieve "j index of 5", our program goes to memory location 1000,
加上内存偏移地址5 这里的值是4
plus an offset of 5, which in this case, holds a value of 4.
有个概念容易搞混 数组里的第5个数 和 数组里索引为5的数
It's easy to confuse the fifth number in the array with the number at index 5.
它们不一样
They are not the same.
记住 索引为5的数是数组中第6个数
Remember, the number index 5 is the 6th number in the array
因为第一个数从0索引开始
cause the first number is at index 0.
数组是很通用的数据结构 它很常用
Arrays are extremely versatile data structures, used all the time,
所以有很多有用的相关函数
and so there are many functions that can handle them to do useful things.
比如 相当多编程语言有内置的排序函数
For example, pretty much every programming language comes with
它接受数组 将其排序后再返回结果
a built-in sort function, where you just pass in your array, and it comes back sorted.
这样就不用从头写排序的算法了
So there's no need to write that algorithm from scratch.
与数组十分相近的是字符串 它是字符的的数组
Very closely related are Strings, which are just arrays of characters,
字符包括字母 数字 标点符号和其他书写符号
like letters, numbers, punctuation and other written symbols.
第4集曾说过计算机如何储存字符
We talked about how computers store characters way back in Episode 4.
通常 新建字符串只需这样用双引号括起来
Most often, to save a string into memory, you just put it in quotes, like so.
虽然看上去不像数组 但确实是
Although it doesn't look like an array, it is.
实际上内存里是这样存储的
Behind the scenes, the memory looks like this.
注意内存中的字符串以0结尾
Note that the string ends with a zero in memory.
不是字符0 而是二进制数0
It's not the character zero, but the binary value 0.
它叫做空字符(结束符) 表示字符串的结尾
This is called the null character, and denotes the end of the string in memory.
空字符很重要 当我调用函数"print quote"时
This is important because if I call a function like "print quote", which writes the string
函数会把字符串显示在屏幕上 它从第一个内存地址依次打印出每个字符
to the screen, it prints out each character in turn starting at the first memory location,
但函数需要知道什么时候停止
but it needs to know when to stop!
否则就会以文本形式打印出内存中的所有内容
Otherwise, it would print out every single thing in memory as text.
0告诉字符串函数该停止了
The zero tells string functions when to stop.
因为计算机经常处理文本
Because computers work with text so often,
所以有很多专门处理字符串的函数
there are many functions that specifically handle strings.
例如 许多编程语言有字符串拼接函数
For example, many programming languages have a string concatenation function,
记作 strcat 它接受两个字符串
or "strcat", which takes in two strings,
把第二个复制到第一个后面
and copies the second one to the end of the first.
数组可以作为一维列表
We can use arrays for making one dimensional lists,
但有时需要操作二维数据
but sometimes you want to manipulate data that is two dimensional,
像是电子表格中的数字 或计算机屏幕的像素
like a grid of numbers in a spreadsheet, or the pixels on your computer screen.
这个需要用矩阵
For this, we need a Matrix.
可以把矩阵想象成以数组为元素的数组
You can think of a Matrix as an array of arrays!
3x3数组其实是一个长度为3的数组
So a 3 by 3 matrix is really an array of size 3,
它的每个元素又是一个长度为3的数组
with each index storing an array of size 3.
如图初始化矩阵
We can initialize a matrix like so.
在内存里 就像这样的顺序保存在一起
In memory, this is packed together in order like this.
要访问(二维数组的)一个元素 需要指定两个索引
To access a value, you need to specify two indexes,
如 j[2][1] 它告诉计算机
like "J index of 2, then index of 1" - this tells the computer
寻找2号子数组 索引为1的元素
you're looking for the item in subarray 2 at position 1.
这样得到数值12
And this would give us the value 12.
矩阵的神奇之处在于它不仅限于3x3的大小
The cool thing about matrices is we're not limited to 3 by 3
它可以是任意大小
- we can make them any size we want
我们也可以按需创建任意维度的矩阵
- and we can also make them any number of dimensions we want.
例如 可以创建一个5维矩阵 并像这样取值
For example, we can create a five dimensional matrix and access it like this.
好 你现在知道5维矩阵如何取值了 告诉朋友吧
That's right, you now know how to access a five dimensional matrix - tell your friends!
我们在数组或矩阵储存单个数字或字母
So far, we've been storing individual numbers or letters into our arrays or matrices.
但储存一块相关变量通常很有用
But often it's useful to store a block of related variables together.
比如你想把银行账号和余额存在一起
Like, you might want to store a bank account number along with its balance.
这样的一组变量可以存储在结构体中
Groups of variables like these can be bundled together into a Struct.
现在可以创建多个数字的变量了
Now we can create variables that aren't just single numbers,
它是复合数据结构 能够一次性储存多个数据
but are compound data structures, able to store several pieces of data at once.
还可以创建自定义结构体的数组
We can even make arrays of structs that we define,
这些结构体在内存中合并存储在一起
which are automatically bundled together in memory.
如果访问 j[0] 就得到该位置的整个结构体
If we access, for example, J index of 0, we get back the whole struct stored there,
然后可以取出指定的银行账号和余额
and we can pull the specific account number and balance data we want.
像其他数组一样 这个结构体数组在创建时长度是固定的
This array of structs, like any other array, gets created at a fixed size
不能再变大
that can't be enlarged to add more items.
此外 数组必须按顺序存在内存中
Also, arrays must be stored in order in memory,
难以在中间插入新元素
making it hard to add a new item to the middle.
但是结构体可以用来创建更复杂的数据结构
But, the struct data structure can be used for
来避开这些限制
building more complicated data structures that avoid these restrictions.
让我们看看称为 节点 的结构体
Let's take a look at this struct that's called a "node".
它保存 一个变量(例如数字) 和 一个指针
It stores a variable, like a number, and also a pointer.
指针是一种特殊的变量 正如其名 它指向一个内存地址
A pointer is a special variable that points, hence the name, to a location in memory.
节点可以用于实现链表
Using this struct, we can create a linked list,
链表是一种灵活多变的数据结构 它可以保存多个节点
which is a flexible data structure that can store many nodes.
链表中的每个节点都会指向下一个节点
It does this by having each node point to the next node in the list.
假设内存中有三个节点
Let's imagine we have three node structs saved in memory,
分别位于1000 1002 和1008
at locations 1000, 1002 and 1008.
因为创建时间不同 所以它们的存储位置未必连续
They might be spaced apart, because they were created at different times,
并且相互之间可能有其他数据
and other data can sit between them.
第一个节点值是 7
So, you see that the first node contains the value 7,
指向地址1008
and the location 1008 in its "next" pointer.
表明链表中的下一个节点位于内存地址1008
This means that the next node in the linked list is located at memory location 1008.
沿着链表找到下一节点
Looking down the linked list, to the next node,
值是112 同时指向地址1002的节点
we see it stores the value 112 and points to another node at location 1002.
然后找到了节点 它的值是14
If we follow that, we find a node that contains the value 14
它又指回了地址1000的第一个节点
and points back to the first node at location 1000.
所以这恰好是个循环链表
So this linked list happened to be circular,
但它也可以是单链表 只要下一个指针的值为0
but it could also have been terminated by using a next pointer value of 0
即是空值 代表链表的尾部
- the null value - which would indicate we've reached the end of the list.
程序员使用链表时
When programmers use linked lists, they rarely look at the memory values
基本不关注指针指向哪里
stored in the next pointers.
而是如上图 使用链表的抽象模型
Instead, they can use an abstraction of a linked list, that looks like this,
这样更容易理解
which is much easier to conceptualize.
数组必须预先指定大小
Unlike an array, whose size has to be pre-defined,
而链表与它不同 可以动态增减大小
linked lists can be dynamically extended or shortened.
比如 我们可以创建新节点 再插入链表
For example, we can allocate a new node in memory, and insert it into this list,
这个过程只用改变指针的指向
just by changing the next pointers.
链表可以轻松的重新排序 缩减 分割 逆序等等
Linked Lists can also easily be re-ordered, trimmed, split, reversed, and so on,
非常简洁高效
which is pretty nifty,
对于上周所说的排序十分有用
and pretty useful for algorithms like sorting, which we talked about last week.
由于它的灵活性
Owing to this flexibility, many more complex data structures
很多复杂数据结构都以链表实现
are built on top of linked lists.
最著名的是队列和栈
The most famous and universal are queues and stacks.
队列 按先来后到顺序执行 就像邮局里排队
A queue - like the line at your post office - goes in order of arrival.
最早来的人先获得服务
The person who has been waiting the longest, gets served first.
你只想买邮票 而你前面那个人却好像要寄23个包裹
No matter how frustrating it is that all you want to do is buying stamps
再怎么不爽(你也只能等着)
and the person in front of you seems to be mailing 23 packages.
这种机制叫做 先进先出 简称FIFO
But, regardless, this behavior is called First-In First-Out, or FIFO.
这才是重点 而不是23个包裹
That's the first part. Not the 23 packages thing.
假设我们有一个名为 "邮局队列" 的指针
Imagine we have a pointer, named "post office queue",
它指向链表的第一个节点
that points to the first node in our linked list.
汉克的服务结束 可以读取汉克的指针
Once we're done serving Hank, we can read Hank's next pointer,
更新"邮局队列"指针 指向队列的下一个人
and update our "post office queue" pointer to the next person in the line.
汉克"出队"了  他完事了
We've successfully dequeued Hank -- he's gone, done, finished.
如果我们想让人"入队" 即把某人加入队列
If we want to enqueue someone, that is, add them to the line,
必须遍历整个链表 直到其尾部
we have to traverse down the linked list until we hit the end,
然后把尾部的指针指向新来的人
and then change that next pointer to point to the new person.
稍微改变下 就能把链表改为栈
With just a small change, we can use linked lists as stacks, which are LIFO…
栈是后进先出 简称LIFO
Last-In First-Out.
你可以把栈看做一堆煎饼
You can think of this like a stack of pancakes...
每做好一个 就把它放在饼堆的最上面
as you make them, you add them to the top of stack.
吃的时候从最上面拿
And when you want to eat one, you take them from the top of the stack.
真好吃！
Delicious!
不像队列称为"入队"和"出队"
Instead of enqueueing and dequeuing,
栈的进出操作 称为"入栈"和"出栈"
data is pushed onto the stack and popped from the stacks.
没错 都是专有名词
Yep, those are the official terms!
如果节点的结构体 不止一个指针 而是有两个
If we update our node struct to contain not just one, but two pointers,
就能构造另一种数据结构 树 很多算法都用到了它
we can build trees, another data structure that's used in many algorithms.
同样的 程序员不看指针的值
Again, programmers rarely look at the values of these pointers,
他们像这样抽象化树的结构：最上面的节点称为根节点
and instead conceptualize trees like this: The top most node is called the root.
任意节点之下的节点都称为子节点
And any nodes that hang from other nodes are called children nodes.
【注：即根节点之下的所有节点都是子节点】
容易猜出 子节点之上的叫父节点
As you might expect, nodes above children are called parent nodes.
【注：图中VP(副总统)节点之上正好是PRESIDENT(总统)节点】
这是不是意味着托马斯·杰斐逊是阿伦·伯尔的父亲呢？
Does this example imply that Thomas Jefferson is the parent of Aaron Burr?
【托马斯·杰斐逊是美国第三任总统，阿伦·伯尔是他在任期间的副总统】
你在同人里怎么写都可以
I'll leave that to your fanfiction to decide.
最后 树的末端 所有没有子节点的节点
And finally, any nodes that have no children - where the tree ends
叫做叶节点
- are called Leaf Nodes.
我们的例子里每个节点最多有两个子节点
In our example, nodes can have up to two children, and for that reason,
所以这个特殊数据结构叫做二叉树
this particular data structure is called a binary tree.
不过你可以随意设置树的子节点数 3个，4个或者其他任意数量
But you could just as easily have trees with three, four or any number of children
通过相应修改数据结构就可以实现
by modifying the data structure accordingly.
你甚至可以创造使用链表实现的树节点
You can even have tree nodes that use linked lists
用来储存所有指向的节点
to store all the nodes they point to.
无论在在现实中还是数据结构中 树的最重要特点
An important property of trees - both in real life and in data structures
是从根节点到叶节点是单向的
- is that there's a one-way path from roots to leaves.
如果根节点连向叶节点 叶节点连向根节点 会有点怪
It'd be weird if roots connected to leaves, that connected to roots.
对于任意连接的数据 包括环状数据在内
For data that links arbitrarily, that include things like loops,
我们则用数据结构 图
we can use a graph data structure instead.
还记得上一集由道路连接的城市图吗
Remember our graph from last episode of cities connected by roads?
它可以用含有许多指针的节点储存 很像树
This can be stored as nodes with many pointers, very much like a tree,
但没有根节点和叶节点 子节点和父节点这些概念
but there is no notion of roots and leaves, and children and parents…
节点间可以任意指向
Anything can point to anything!
计算机的这些基本数据结构 我们差不多突击讲完了
So that's a whirlwind overview of pretty much all of the fundamental data structures
used in computer science.
在此基础上 程序员创建了各种各样精巧的新算法
On top of these basic building blocks, programmers have built all sorts of
它们的性质略有不同
clever variants, with slightly different properties - data structures like
例如红黑树 堆 我们没时间讲了
red-black trees and heaps, which we don't have time to cover.
这些不同的数据结构
These different data structures have properties
适合某些特定计算
that are useful for particular computations.
正确选择数据结构可以极大简化工作
The right choice of data structure can make your job a lot easier, so it pays off
所以开始写代码前 值得花时间思考如何组织数据
to think about how you want to structure your data before you jump in.
幸运的是 大部分编程语言
Fortunately, most programming languages come with libraries
都有包含现成数据结构的库
packed full of ready-made data structures.
例如 C++的STL标准模板库
For example, C++ has its Standard Template Library,
Java的JCL Java类库
and Java has the Java Class Library.
程序员就不必浪费时间从头实现功能
These mean programmers don't have to waste time implementing things from scratch,
而能利用数据结构做更多有趣的事情
and can instead wield the power of data structures to do more interesting things,
我们的抽象也更进了一步
once again allowing us to operate at a new level of abstraction!
下周见
I'll see you next week.
阿尔法小分队荣誉译制
翻：@ErrorEnvyEnchant 校：@Auriance 压制：@Mihael_Ho
长期招募 详情见微博置顶@阿尔法小分队科教组